《生活大爆炸》前情提要
Previously on The Big Bang Theory...
-这是什么  -没什么
- What's this? - Oh, nothing,
一些我们用不着的数学
just some math we don't need.
这是另一种方案
This is a different approach.
你们是想把这个导向系统做得更小吗
You trying to get the guidance system even smaller?
这只是纸上谈兵  都还没算出来呢
It's just a... theory. Well, it's not even worked out.
我要这个方案
I want this.
但我们已经做到之前约定的规格了
Uh, but we've already met the agreed upon specs.
将规格变小需要花好几周重新计算
Going smaller would require weeks' worth of new computations.
那就让那个长袖套短袖的小孩做啊
So get the kid with the two shirts to do it.
长官  请容许我说一句
Sir, I mean, if I may,
我们已经花费大量的心思和功夫在现在这台原型机上
uh, we've put a lot of thought and effort into this current prototype.
这真的是一个完美的方案了  最重要的是  它可以实现
It's a really elegant solution,and most importantly, it works.
你们俩说得都非常有道理
You both make excellent points.
感谢你们如此清晰地表达出来
And thank you for presenting it so articulately.
把这个方案做出来
Make this.
时至今日
-香槟  香槟  -谢谢
-Champagne,champagne.  - Thank you.
以及全世界身高最高二年级生的苹果汁
and for the world's tallest second grader, apple juice.
连可弯曲吸管都没有  好一个派对啊
No bendy straw, some party.
敬个酒  谢谢你们在
Hey, a-a toast. Thank you all for your support
我们做这个空军项目时给予的各种支持
while we worked on our Air Force project.
希望你们明白  我们的成功有你们的一份功劳
And please know that we could not have done it without you,
-干杯  -干杯
-so cheers.  -Cheers.
很感激你愿意答谢我们  但这是属于你们的成就
You know, it's nice of you to acknowledge us,but this is your accomplishment.
对啊  你们仨齐心协力把它完成了
Yeah, you guys did this all on your own.
三缺一
Without me.
敬抛下拉杰并获取成功一杯
To success without Raj.
那接下来呢
So what happens next?
第二阶段  测试它  再完善它  然后祈祷自己命长到足以
Phase two, we test it, perfect it, and hope to live long enough
看到由超帅气演员来扮演我们的传记电影
to see the movie based on our lives starring more attractive versions of us.
我肯定能活够久  维他命C
Yeah, I'll definitely live long enough.Vitamin C.
明早第一件事  就是我们仨继续开工
First thing tomorrow morning, we're back at it.
继续三缺一
Without me.
希望他这个角色不会被写进电影里  太扫兴了
I hope his character doesn't make it into the movie,he's kind of a bummer.
莱纳德·霍夫斯塔德  允许进入
Leonard Hofstadter. Access granted.
就算这玩意会烧掉我的视网膜也没关系
I don't care if this thing's burning out my retinas;
它让人家感觉好特别
it makes me feel special.
在我们实地测试前  我们...
Now, before we field test, I think we...
-什么鬼  -东西都去哪了
-What the hell?  -Where is everything?
还有谁有进入许可
Who else has access to this room?
这是机密建筑里的安全实验室
It's a secure lab in a classified facility;
只有美国政府与我们才可进入
only the U.S. Government and us.
好令人不安啊
This is very disconcerting.
但我们的电影一下就精彩了起来
But the movie did just get good.
第十季  第二十三集
长官  抱歉  但我就是想不明白
Sir, I-I-I'm sorry but I just don't get it.
你大半夜跑进我们的实验室
Y-You came into our lab in the middle of the night
拿走我们的原型机与实验成果完全不知会我们一声吗
and took our prototype and all of our research and didn't even tell us?
听起来你已经想明白了啊
Sounds like you get it.
你为什么要这么做
Well, why would you do that?
你们完成了第一阶段  剩下我们来接手就行
You guys completed phase one, we'll take it from here.
你把东西转移到哪里了
Where did you move it?
无可奉告
I can't tell you that.
你要施行第二阶段计划吗
Are you implementing phase two?
无可奉告
I can't tell you that.
所以你打算抢走我们
Wait, so you're just going to take all the work we've done
过去一整年的成果  然后把我们一脚踢开
for the last year and toss us aside?
这个我能告诉你们  是的
That one I can tell you, yes.
这好令人伤心啊
This is all very upsetting.
听到你伤心我也很遗憾
I'm sorry to hear that.
毕竟美国军方的主要焦点就放在
As you know, the primary focus
照顾人民情感上了
of the United States military is people's feelings.
如果你是在讽刺  请留去讽刺我国的敌人
If that's sarcasm, please save it for our enemies.
我可能很快就搬走了  我找到地方住了
Well, I may be moving out soon. I think I found a place to live.
真不想听到你要搬走
Oh, I'm sorry to hear that.
真心的吗  你一直给我发公寓租赁广告
Really? You kept sending me apartment listings.
这个嘛  我...  好吧  我无力反驳
Um... well, I... yeah, you got me.
-你要搬去哪里  -什么时候搬  还有搬去哪里
-Where are you moving?  -And when? But a-also where?
伯特有一间房出租
Bert has a room for rent.
所以你要跟伯特当室友吗
So you're gonna be roommates with Bert?
不是  其实那房间挺私密的
Uh, no, it's, uh, pretty private, actually,
在他的车库楼上
it's over his garage.
所以我唯一会见到他的时间是他停车进来
So the only time I'll see him is when he pulls his car in,
洗衣服或在我餐厅练鼓的时候
does his laundry or practices drums in my dining room.
那挺好的  其实我也有个消息要分享
Well, good for you. I actually have a little news myself.
好吧  话题会回到他什么时候搬走吗
Okay, we're just gonna circle back to when he's moving out?
算了  没关系
Okay, that's cool.
我受邀赴普林斯顿大学任访问学者
I was, uh, asked to be a visiting researcher at Princeton.
-太厉害了  真棒  -恭喜你
-Hey, that's amazing.Good for you.  -Congratulations.
谢谢  但问题是我得离开几个月
Thanks, but the thing is I'll be gone for a few months
我不知道谢尔顿会对此作何感想
and I don't know how Sheldon's gonna feel about that.
拜托  他是个成年人  完全可以照顾自己
Oh, come on, he's a grown man, he can take care of himself.
你真的这么认为吗
You really believe that?
我再次无力反驳
Once again, you got me.
你努力了一年的心血  他们怎么可以就这样夺走
How can you work on something for a year and they just take it?
真不敢相信美国空军会这样对我们
I can't believe the Air Force would treat us like that.
我很想从今天开始不再交税
You know, I have a good mind to stop paying my taxes.
我超享受计算税费的过程  可惜了
It's too bad I enjoy doing them so much.
美国空军又出手了  他们要抹去我们的生活
The Air Force did it again. They're erasing our lives!
这是三楼  走错公寓了
Third floor, wrong apartment.
不过如果有人要把你们公寓清空  然后消失  那人一定是佩妮
Although, if anyone's gonna clean out your apartment and disappear,it'd be Penny.
她可能会消失  但要想她会清任何东西  那是不可能的
She might disappear,but she's definitely not cleaning anything.
没事  一切都在
It's okay, everything's here.
发生什么事了
Oh, hey, what's going on?
说了你们也不会信  军方没收了我们整个项目
You won't believe it,the military confiscated our project.
-什么  -开玩笑吧  他们为什么要这么做
- What? - You're kidding. Why would they do that?
无可奉告
They wouldn't say.
我深深地觉得被背叛了
I feel so betrayed.
我此生一直以为山姆大叔[美国政府]是
You know, all my life I thought Uncle Sam
友好会送人礼物那种大叔
was a friendly uncle who brought you presents.
结果他恰恰相反
It turns out he's the other kind.
谢尔顿  真是太遗憾了
Sheldon, I'm so sorry.
多谢关心  我们能聊点别的吗
Thank you. Can we just talk about something else?
对啊  你们有什么消息要分享吗
Yeah, what's going on with you guys?
给我们来点好消息
Give us some good news.
艾米有话说
Amy's got some news.
是的
Yeah, um...
拉杰要搬走了
Raj is moving out.
不要啊  什么时候
Oh, no. When?
你还好吧
You doing okay?
不好
Not really.
用我给你放尼尔·戴蒙德的歌吗  你每次听了都会开心点
Want me to put on some Neil Diamond? That always makes you feel better.
美国杰出老牌歌手
不用了  你听一听就会开始发情  而我现在没心情
No. Then you'll get all sexed up and I'm not in the mood.
整整一年都白费了
I mean, an entire year wasted.
你或许忘记了去年你还有一项成就
You might be forgetting another accomplishment of the past year.
是是是  我们还将一个小生命带来人世
Yeah, yeah, we brought life into the world.
不是吧  你就这么形容我们生孩子的重要性吗
Really? That's the importance you put on us having a baby?
我对此当然开心啊  但我又没怎么出力
I'm happy about it, but, I mean, it's not like I did much.
我是说  前三分钟过后  剩下的都是你的功劳
I mean, after the first three minutes it was pretty much all you.
你跟他说了去普林斯顿大学的事了吗
So, did you tell him about Princeton yet?
还没  我想等他心情好时再说
No, I'm waiting till he's in a good mood.
亲爱的  那你可能活不到那个时候
Oh, sweetie, you might not live that long.
我不知道  或许我不该走
I don't know, maybe I shouldn't go.
别闹了  他会没事的
Oh, stop it, he'll be fine.
应该吧  反正他还有你和莱纳德  你们就住在对门
I guess. And he'll have you and Leonard right across the hall the whole time.
糟糕  等等  或许你不该走
Oh, damn, wait, you know, maybe you shouldn't go...
挂了啊  早上好
Got to go. Morning.
我为占用超过分配好的如厕时间道歉
I apologize for exceeding my allotted bathroom time.
你还好吗
Are you feeling okay?
不好  貌似悲伤会影响人如厕的规律性
Not really. Apparently grief can make one less regular.
听到这个消息我也很难过
Oh, I'm sorry to hear that.
我坐在马桶上等了又等  但徒劳无功
No, I sat and I sat, but to no avail.
细节越多  我越难过
Oh, the-the more details, the more sorry.
或许这个能让你开心一点
Well, maybe this'll cheer you up.
我做了你最喜欢的燕麦片  什么都没加
I made your favorite oatmeal...plain.
今天是什么好日子啊
What's the occasion?
没什么  我只是想做点让你开心的事
No occasion, I just wanted to do something nice for you.
你人真好
You're so kind.
真不知道认识你之前  我是怎么活过来的
You know, I don't know how I ever got by without you.
你嘴真甜  但你之前一个人也活得好好的
That's sweet, but you... you did just fine on your own.
我本来也以为是这样  但我逐渐意识到
Well, I thought that, too, but I've come to realize,
我对你十分依赖
I am completely dependent on you.
谢尔顿  说什么傻话
Sheldon, you're, you're being silly.
不  每天早上醒来
No, to wake up every morning
知道你在身边我都感到很安心
and know you're there is a great comfort to me.
寡淡无味
Mmm, tasteless.
你手艺怎么那么巧
How do you do it?
你现在要做的就是  忘掉这个空军项目
You know, what you need to do is put this Air Force project behind you
把精力投入新的研究
and just dive into something new.
倒是可以投入我们的量子认知试验
Well, there is our quantum cognition experiment.
我和你可以多花点时间在那上面
You and I could spend more time on that.
我说不好  就算我们
Oh, I don't know,I mean, let's say we succeed
成功证明了我们的意识创造现实
in proving that our consciousness creates reality.
那也算不上什么伟大成就
I mean, what will we have really accomplished?
一块面包还是卖三块钱啊
You know, a loaf of bread's still three bucks.
我不懂了  是你总说希望有更多时间和我相处
I'm confused. You're always saying that you want to spend more time with me.
对  我是这么说过
That is true, I have said that.
你整天说  真的很烦
Well, a lot, it's very annoying.
发生什么变化了吗
Has something changed?
你是不是有事瞒着我
Um, is there something that you're not telling me?
我得到了普林斯顿大学的夏季研究奖学金
I was offered a summer research fellowship at Princeton.
普林斯顿吗  很不错的大学
Princeton? A fine institution.
阿尔伯特·爱因斯坦教过书的地方
The place where Albert Einstein taught.
莱纳德也是在那里拿到博士学位  所以那学校可能没落了
And where Leonard got his PhD, so it may have gone downhill.
对  就是那所
Yeah, that's the one.
这是很棒的消息  恭喜你
Well, that's wonderful. Congratulations.
我还没接受  我想先跟你商量一下
Well, I-I haven't accepted it yet. I wanted to talk to you first.
有什么好商量的  你必须接受  这很重要
Wh-What is there to talk about? You have to take it. It's important.
-你也很重要  -谢谢  但我不会有事的
-So are you.  -Thank you, but I'll be fine.
你确定吗
Are-are you sure?
是的  虽然我可能失去了导向系统和女友
Yes. I may have lost my guidance system and my girlfriend,
但我结肠里还有昨天吃的食物陪伴着我
but I still have a colon full of yesterday's meals to keep me company.
不过  因为你做的高纤早餐
Although, thanks to your high-fiber breakfast,
它们很快也要离我而去了
I'm sure that'll be leaving me, too.
真的吗  他都不往里面加葡萄干或香蕉片那些吗
Really? He doesn't put raisins or banana slices or anything in it?
我觉得纯燕麦不是这件事的重点
I don't think plain oatmeal was the point of that story.
-我是喜欢加点红糖啦  -姐妹们
-I mean, I like a little brown sugar...  -Guys.
-抱歉  -不好意思  你还是会去的吧
- Sorry. - Sorry. You're still gonna go, right?
我也不知道  谢尔顿现在那么脆弱
I don't know. Sheldon's so vulnerable right now.
听着  如果你们角色调换
Oh, come on. Look, if the roles were reversed,
他会马上坐第一班火车去新泽西
he'd be on the first train to New Jersey,
如果第一班上有青少年的话  他会搭第二班
or the second train if there were teenagers on the first one.
再说距离不见得是坏事啊
Well, distance might be nice.
上次华仔完成一个大型项目后
The last time a big project ended for Howie,
我到哪儿他都要跟着
he wouldn't stop following me around.
我去做乳腺X光检查他也要一起去
He even went with me to get a mammogram.
那有什么问题
Well, what's wrong with that?
他想跟我一起做检查  跟某种诡异的情侣按摩似的
No, he wanted to get one with me, like some kind of weird couple's massage.
然而你还是给他生了孩子  厉害
And yet you bore his child. Neato.
你还是对这个机会感到兴奋的  对吧
You're excited about this opportunity, right?
当然了  我能成为第一组
Of course. I get to be part of the first team
使用氡标记来映射结构...
to use radon markers to map the structures that...
行了  说"是的"就够了
Okay, a simple yes will do.
-你一定要去  -我知道  可如果谢尔顿...
-You have to go.  -I know, but what if Sheldon...
听我说  就算分隔两地一阵子  你们俩的感情也不会受影响
Okay, listen to me. Your relationship can handle being long distance for a while.
你们俩本来"亲密"接触也不多
It's not like you two are very physical.
你又不知道我们关起门来都干了什么
Hey, you don't know what goes on behind closed doors.
总给你讲课吗
A lot of lectures?
看来你还真知道
All right, so you know.
相信我  如果你不去  你会后悔一辈子
I'm telling you, if you don't go you'll end up regretting it.
等等我
Wait up! ?
又来了
Oh, great.
你有东西忘记带了哦
You left something at home.
人家的爱心大抱抱
A big hug!
还有人家的爱心小亲亲
I found it right next to these kisses.
我已经没救了  你快逃吧
It's too late for me. Save yourself.
又要有自己的窝了  开心吗
So, are you excited to have your own place again?
-开心  不过我会想你们的  -我们也会想你的
-I am, but I'll miss you guys.  -Ah, we'll miss you, too.
那...你说这话时能把那抹窃笑抑制住吗
Wha... you could try saying that without smiling.
我尽量了  但实在是忍不住呀
I'm trying. This is the best I can do.
你在干什么
What are you doing?
你们看我像在干嘛
What does it look like?
我在吹奏悲伤的口琴曲啊
I'm playing sad harmonica...
在一间四壁空空犹如我心空空的公寓里
in an apartment as empty as my heart.
发生什么事了
Why?
人家忧郁了  我的宝贝要离我而去
I got the blues. My baby done left me.
拜托  谢尔顿
Come on, Sheldon.
艾米不过是去几个月而已
Amy's only gone for a few months.
现在我搬走了  你的旧房间也空出来了
And now that I'm moving out, your old room is empty,
你随时随地都可以回去住啊
so you can stay there whenever you want.
能和你在过道上聊两句吗
Uh, could I talk to you in the hall for a sec?
可以呀
Yeah, sure.
谢尔顿  你别犯傻了
Sheldon, you're being silly.
我在犯傻吗  昨天我还在负责空军项目
Am I? Yesterday I had an Air Force project,
有个同居的女友  好朋友拉杰就住在我对门
a girlfriend who lived with me, and my good friend Raj right across the hall.
你真的在意最后这一点吗
Do you really care about that last one?
不在意  他是给我这单子凑数的
No, but that list was sounding a little thin.
别光想不好的事   换个角度看问题
Instead of dwelling on the negative, think about this.
你的女朋友得到了如此珍贵的机会
Your girlfriend was given an amazing opportunity,
也让你可以借机向她展现
which gives you an opportunity to show her
你是个能给她爱与支持的男友
that you're a loving and supportive boyfriend.
所以要唬弄她
So trick her.
让我重新说一遍  你和艾米
All right, let me start again.Uh... you and Amy...
我能先把东西拿出来吗  听起来你还得解释好一段时间呢
Can I get my stuff? Sounds like it's gonna be a while.
人家好想你
I missed you.
-过来  我们聊聊  -哦
-Come here, let's talk.  -Ooh.
听起来很严重  是我太调皮
Sounds serious. Have I been a bad boy?
-你要打人家的小屁股了吗  你知道我...  -安静听我说
-Am I gonna get a spanking 'cause you know I...  -Just listen.
我不知道你有没有发现
I don't know if you realize this,
但每次你手上没有项目时  你就变得没有安全感
but whenever you're between projects,you tend to get a little insecure.
有点黏人
A little clingy.
我知道  人家错错啦
I know and I'm sorry.
好了好了  住手
Oh, oh, oh, okay, stop.
停下来  我喜欢你情深款款的时候  但你这不是正常的反应
Stop.I love when you're affectionate,but this is not coming from a good place.
哎哟喂  那你上次花了两年时间研发过敏药
Well, excuse me,but what did you do when you worked on that allergy drug
最后研究却被药监局枪毙时呢
for two years and the FDA shut down your project?
我替咱俩报名了交际舞的课
I signed us up for ballroom dance class.
很好  还有你那一次被踢出抗真菌药团队的时候呢
Okay, and what did you do when they took you off the antifungal team?
我逼着你让我怀孕了
I made us have a baby.
所以结论是
So?
放马过来吧
Bring it in.
本电影刚刚被评为限制级
And now the movie just got rated "R."
你要去哪里吗
You going somewhere?
不  是你要走  所以我送你这个作为礼物
No, but you are,so I got you this as a present.
谢尔顿  你不用这么做
Sheldon, that isn't necessary.
不  我需要  莱纳德告诉我
No, it is. Leonard pointed out to me
我并不是一个时常能给予你爱与支持的男朋友
that I'm not always a loving and supportive boyfriend,
所以我给你买了高质量的行李箱
so here's some quality luggage.
谢谢
Thank you.
售货员说坠机这箱子都不会有事  所以...
The salesman said it could survive a plane crash, so...
也许你应该坐在箱子里面飞
Perhaps you should fly inside it.
这是说你同意我离开吗
Does this mean you're okay with me going?
我并不期待
Well, I'm not looking forward to it,
但这是千载难逢的机会  你必须接受
but it is a wonderful opportunity and you need to take it.
而且  普林斯顿在新泽西
Besides, Princeton is in New Jersey,
所以我也不用怕你会想赖着不走
so it's not like you're gonna want to stay.
我知道今天不是你的生日  但如果你有性趣...
Uh, I know it's not your birthday,but if you're interested...
-我有  -好
- I am. - Okay.
我得说清楚
Oh, and just to be clear,
我和你亲热  并不是为了把你留下
I'm not being intimate with you in order to keep you from going.
我没这样想
I wasn't thinking that.
不  我只是警告你
Well, no, it's just, I'm just warning you, you know,
当你发现自己在五千公里之外渴望得到这诱人的身躯
if you find yourself 3,000 miles away and craving a-a hit of this, you know...
我不能通过视频给你
...I can't Skype it to you.
我愿意冒这个险
That's a risk I'm willing to take.
那好吧  我们进卧室
All right, then. Let's go to the bedroom,
除去衣衫  叠得整整齐齐
remove our clothes, fold them neatly...
再开始狂野性爱
...and engage in frenzied lovemaking.
如果我们不叠衣服呢
What if we don't fold our clothes at all?
我...或者  如果我们叠好呢
I'd... or... what if we fold them?
-钥匙还给你们  -谢谢
-Well, here's your key back.  -Thank you.
我把家里布置好就请你们过去玩
As soon as I have the place set up I'm gonna have you guys over.
感谢邀请
Oh, we would love that.
你们收留我  我真是感激不尽
I really can't thank you enough for taking me in.
我处在人生的低谷  还有...
You know, I was in a pretty low place in my life, and...
艾米  你这个顽皮的小妖精
Oh, Amy, you naughty vixen.
总之  我刚说到
Anyway, uh, as I was saying,
我处在人生的低谷中  还有
I was at a pretty low place in my life and, uh,
如果没有你们这样的好朋友
if it wasn't for friends like you...
我的天  这种刺激方式太高效了
My goodness, that form of stimulation is highly efficient.
哥比不过他们  拜
I can't compete with that. Bye.
我们应该给他们点隐私吗
Should we give them their privacy?
我想  但我做不到
I want to, but I don't think I can.
-爽  -好了  听够了
- Whoopee! - Okay, I'm good now.
车在等我  你要送我下楼吗
Okay, the car is waiting. Do you want to walk me downstairs?
当然  让我来拿
Of course. Here, here, let me.
我对新泽西做了下调研
I've been doing a little research on New Jersey,
我很高兴地得知  他们的主要农产品是草皮
and I was delighted to learn that their chief agricultural product is sod.
-是吗  -没错
- Is it? - Hmm, yes.
也许我以前对他们的态度太严厉了
Yeah, perhaps I've been harder on them than they deserve.
你觉得有没可能你会享受一段独处的时光呢
Do you think it's possible you might enjoy being on your own for a little while?
很难说  我从来没真正一个人住过
It's hard to say. I've never really lived by myself.
如果我变得古怪又神经怎么办
What if I become strange and eccentric?
无论怎样我都爱你
I'll love you no matter what.
比如霍华德·休斯把自己的尿存在牛奶瓶里
Howard Hughes saved his urine in milk bottles.
电影制片人 导演 企业家
真有这天  船到桥头自然直
We'll cross that bridge when we come to it.
你到机场后会发短信给我吗
And you'll text me when you arrive at the airport?
-会  -到登机口也会吗
- I will.  -And when you're at the gate?
如果你在头等舱看到《权力的游戏》里的演员呢
And if you see any actors from Game of Thrones in first class?
我不知道他们的样子  不过我会的
I don't know what they look like, but sure.
-到了后别忘跟我视频  -好的
- And don't forget to Skype me when you arrive. - I won't.
-每天早上  -明白
- And every morning. - Got it.
当然  我这边9点  你那边已经是中午了
Now of course, my 9:00 A.M. is your noon,
咱们直接避免"早上好"  "中午好"的误区
so let's avoid the whole "Good morning," "Good afternoon" minefield,
直接说"你好"吧
and let's just say, "Hello."
想得真周到
Good thinking.
记住  我为你感到骄傲  你做什么我都支持你
And just remember, I am proud of you and I support you in all that you do.
谢谢你  意义重大
Thank you. That means a lot.
还有一件事  如果你在工作中碰到一位男性科学家
Oh, and one last thing. If you find yourself working with a male scientist
他和我一样聪明一样高大  留着雷神索尔的发型
who's as smart as me, as tall as me and has hair like Thor,
我要你马上远离现场  立刻给我打电话
well, then I want you to step away from the situation and call me immediately.